Guide to the Northwest Tribal Oral History interviews 1963-1973
Center for Pacific Northwest Studies
- Audio Recordings, 1963-1973; Series I; 33999
  - Louisa George, Sarah James, Ella Reid, Philoemina Solomon (Harry), Helen Paul, Rosemary Placid and Ernest Paul, Nooksack and Lummi Elders (Part I), 1973 April 27 (Box 1, Tape 33)
    Tape 33: Topics covered in this interview include: Nooksack delineation; traditional fishing implements and materials; traditional floral and faunal resources- used for food, shelter, and clothing; boarding schools and educational experiences; early missionaries- i.e. Father Cheriouse; why the Nooksacks were not at the Point Elliot Treaty signing; longhouse location and construction; traditional dyes; appropriate etiquette at a gathering; and more on boarding school life. Words in Halkomalem, Lhacheslum (Nooksack), Skagit, and Lummi are transcribed using the Lummi alphabet system. Transcript available.
  - Louisa George, Sarah James, Ella Reid, Philoemina Solomon (Harry), Helen Paul, Rosemary Placid and Ernest Paul, Nooksack and Lummi Elders (Part II), 1973 April 27 (Box 1, Tape 34)
    Tape 34: This tape is a continuation of the interview that started on tape 33. Topics covered include: Introductions and personal identifications, and traditional marriage practices (partial). Words in Lummi and Skagit are transcribed using the Lummi alphabet system. Transcript available.
  - Joe Louie and Nooksack Women (Part I), 1973 May 1 (Box 1, Tape 35)
    Tape 35, Side One: Transcript available.
    Tape 35, Side Two: Blank
  - Joe Louie and Nooksack Women (Part II), 1973 May 1 (Box 1, Tape 36)
    Tape 36, Side One: Transcript available.
    Tape 36, Side Two: Transcript available.
  - Louisa George, Ella Reid, and Helen Paul, Nooksack Elders (Part I), 1973 May 9 (Box 1, Tape 37)
    Tape 37: Topics covered in this interview include: Experiences with early Indian education policies of acculturation and assimilation through the boarding schools and reservation mission schools, early industrial opportunities for Nooksack people, land appropriation and compensation, some on Shaker religion and Methodist diffusion, Native language loss and restoration programs for the Nooksack language, traditional funerary customs, dancing and spirit doctoring. All Indian words are transcribed using the Lummi alphabet. Transcript available.
  - Louisa George, Ella Reid, and Helen Paul, Nooksack Elders (Part I) (MISSING), 1973 May 9 (Box 1, Tape 38)
    Tape 38: Conclusion of the interview which began on tape 37. Tape 38 does not exist in the collection at CPNWS.
  - Morrie Alexander, Lummi master carver, 1973 April (Box 1, Tape 39)
    Tape 39: [Poor recording quality] This speech at the Lummi Tribal Center given is a brief version of the one contained on tape 40.
  - Morrie Alexander, Lummi master carver, 1973 April (Box 1, Tape 40)
    Tape 40: Appearance at VU (possibly Viking Union at WWU?)
  - Morrie Alexander, Lummi master carver, 1973 April (Box 1, Tape 41)
    Tape 41: Similar to the lectures given on tape 31 and 32, however question and answer periods vary. This lecture given to CES class was held in the Viking Union on the campus of Western Washington University. Topics covered include: An introduction to the distinguishing features of Northwest Coast Indians, original use and inhabitation of the San Juan Islands, land mammal hunting- including materials and implements, traditional fishing implements- including materials used for making nets, hooks, traps, and weirs, duck hunting, snares, materials used for carving, masks- including who can wear them and when, naming ceremonies- including a description of the process or work involved. Question and answer period follows the lecture where questions concerning raiding and slavery are addressed. All Lummi words are transcribed using the Lummi alphabet. Transcript available.
  - Christine Bosler, James McKay, James McKay Jr., and Rosemary Placid, Lummi Elders (Part I), 1973 June 1 (Box 1, Tape 42)
    Tape 42: Topics covered in this interview include: Genealogy, position of the "chief" within the community, early leaders including chief Tsi'li'xw, Chow'its'soot, and Kwina, repercussions of the Allotment Act, early industries, raiding and battles fought with the Northern peoples, and boarding school experiences. All Lummi names and words are transcribed using the Lummi alphabet. Transcript available.
  - Christine Bosler, James McKay, James McKay Jr., and Rosemary Placid, Lummi Elders (Part II), 1973 June 1 (Box 1, Tape 43)
    Tape 43: Conclusion to the interview started on tape 42. Topics covered include: Boarding school experiences, modern issues including militancy, racism, land trust disputes, Bureau of Indian Affairs, the economy on the Lummi reservation, modern fishing, and treaty grievances. Transcript available.
  - Pilot Meeting: Swinomish Elders, interviewed by Landy James in LaConner, Washington., 1973 May 15 (Box 1, Tape 44)
    Tape 44, Side One: Morris Dan and his wife Bertha. Ken House, John Sheridan and William Baylis are students enrolled in the class. Bertha and Morris Dan express their concern over having the non-native students there. Bertha speaks about previous researchers who came in and take as fact the words of one individual. She is concerned that her words will be used improperly. Landy James, one of the interviewers, defends the practice of taping interviews with the elders as a means of cultural preservation for Indian people. Morris and Bertha Dan continue to rebuke the idea of having their words taped and taken away. A lengthy discussion of the goals of the project follows. Morris Dan speaks about the importance of knowing your family line. Bertha speaks about the division of the Swinomish people into certain sections on the reservation. Morris Dan speaks about the inclusion of the Samish, Lower Skagits and other groups on the Swinomish reservation when the land was allotted. Bertha and Morris try to figure out how many families are represented in the room.
    Tape 44, Side Two: Various talk. Landy James speaks about the importance of hearing from more than one family on an issue. Morris speaks about the formation of the reservation under the Indian Homestead Act of 1887. Morris Dan speaks to Landy James' lineage. Discussion of when would be the best time meet again. Morris Dan tells a story about Doug, his grandson. Morris speaks about the ties between the Samish and the Swinomish. Morris and Bertha Dan speak about the young woman researcher that lived among the Swinomish and then took the information she accumulated and left the area with it. The many examples of this kind of exploitation have created a great amount of cautiousness for future such endeavors.
  - Swinomish reservation, interviewed by Landy James, 1973 May 22 (Box 1, Tape 45)
    Tape 45: Landy hands out a couple of sheets that the people present and take some time to look over. [a basketball game in the background makes it difficult to hear the questions that are asked] Landy discusses some of the conceptions attached to being an Indian in the modern world. Landy discusses the idea of shame and the family that helps bring the person around. Landy speaks about the ritualistic nature of time. A question is asked about the growing importance for Western education for the Native American student. Landy speaks to why education is becoming a source of pride for families. Landy speaks about the traditional territory of the Swinomish. [Recording switches to high speed and fades out.]
  - Affiliated Tribes of Northwest Indians Executive Council Meeting in Spokane, 1973 April 12 (Box 1, Tape 46)
    Tape 46, Side One: Meeting begins in progress with Lucy introducing Webster Two Hawk. Mr. Two Hawk speaks about being new to Indian political affairs. He begins by explaining what his organization is seeking. The duties/mission statement for the members of the National Tribal Chairman's Association. Mr. Two Hawk is a Chairman of the Rosebud Sioux tribe. He outlines some of his and his people's frustrations with current and past Indian policies of the Federal government. Speaks to the Indian tribes' right to self-government. Mr. Two Hawk lists his tribe's grievances with the Federal government. Of these is the impossibility of tribal self-determination under the present structure of Indian policies. Mr. Two Hawk presents a projection to remedy the current situation, and aid in the establishment of self-determination for Indian Nations. Mr. Two Hawk speaks to allowing the tribe full control over education for their Indian children without interference by the BIA. He speaks of not equating self-determination with termination. The next speaker is introduced, Executive Director of the National Tribal Chairman's Association, Bill [Yulley]. Mr. Yulley speaks about the origin of the National Tribal Chairman's Association, which was founded for the leaders of the Federally recognized tribes who live and work with reservation policy.
    Tape 46, Side Two: The next speaker is introduced, Chairman Robert Jim of Yakama reservation. Mr. Jim speaks about upholding the treaty rights for the benefit of his people over all other things. Mr. Jim speaks about the proliferation of tribal policies, which see no action. Mr. Jim speaks about the function of the National Tribal Chairman's Association, who he feels represents all tribes with a land base. He feels the integrity of the NTCA is in jeopardy. He speaks of the danger of the Federal Government appending tribal land. He speaks to the function of such groups like the NTCA and the NCAI in reclaiming funds from the Federal Government that have not been rightfully distributed to the Indian tribes. Announcements are made and the next speaker is introduced. Nez Perce member Walter [Moltuck]. Mr. Moltuck reads a resolution he received from a different tribe that is an appeal for communication between Indian Nations. He speaks to the divided nature of Indian groups who are looking outside themselves for leaders. He speaks about FBI monitoring on the Spokane reservation and other Indian Nations. He speaks to tribal unity through an organization movement and a utilization of groups such as the NCTA and the NCAI.
  - Affiliated Tribes of Northwest Indians Conference (1973 Fishing Controversy) (Box 1, Tape 47)
    Tape 47, Side One: The meeting begins in progress with a speaker asking for an endorsement from the NCTA. Speaks about the urgency of the situation, which calls for a unity of Indian peoples, and the forgiveness of past grudges between tribes that will facilitate the lobby for fishing resolutions. Another speaker relating his experiences as an Indian fisherman confronting the myth that it's Indian fishing that is depleting the resource. The speaker dispels this myth, and speaks of the monopoly that the white man has on commercial fishing. The speaker introduces Mike Taylor, an attorney working for the Indian tribes to secure treaty fishing rights. Doug speaks about his organization, The Native American Rights to [Hunt], which is a law firm expert in treaty cases that work to protect tribal sovereignty. Speaks about pending suits, such as the suit against the Army Corps of Engineers on the Columbia River who are involved in the modification of the dams along the Columbia River, which is resulting in the loss of traditional fishing sites for the Tribes along the Columbia River. The questions asked to the attorneys are difficult to decipher. An unidentified speaker with the attorneys speaks about providing physical protection for Native people so they can fish unmolested. Dave [Weir] & Jenny speak about a report that shows where the fish are really going. [The woman speaker is very hard to hear over the background noise] Negotiations between Canada and American Native fishing tribes. Annual catch of Coho salmon in the Puget Sound, by percentage taken by group. [Last five minutes of the tape are damaged]
    Tape 47, Side Two: [Tape is damaged, or recording is very poor for about the first seven minutes.] Speaker calls for a list of grievances from every fishing tribe. Explains articles of incorporation and bylaws as they pertain to fishing. Another speaker breaks in and speaks about the wish of the Canadian Indians to become involved in the fight for the right to fish as the treaty guarantees. A speaker from the Klamath people speaks to his grievances, and knowledge of traditional fishing land where the government says there is none. The lawyers address the issue of land the tribe claims to be traditional hunting and fishing grounds, but that is not recognized or protected by the Federal Government. The lawyer speaks of the process of ethno-historical reconstruction that must be completed for the Courts to recognize and protect traditionally utilized land. The Chairman of the committee lists the resolutions, and these resolutions are discussed and added to.
  - Affiliated Tribes of Northwest Indians Executive Council Meeting, Timber Conference, 1973 April 12 (Box 1, Tape 48)
    Tape 48: Tape is irreparably damaged, due to degradation. No access tape available.
  - Affiliated Tribes of Northwest Indians Executive Council Conference, Spokane, WA, NCAI - NTCA, Cook/Trimble, 1973 April 12 (Box 1, Tape 49)
    Tape 49: Tape is irreparably damaged due to degradation.
  - Affiliated Tribes of Northwest Indians Executive Council Meeting. Spokane, Washington. Indian Rights, Fishing, Nation, 1973 April 12 (Box 1, Tape 50)
    Tape 50, Side One: Speakers are difficult to decipher, as recording is poor. Some discussion of fishing rights and treaty bylaws. Discussion of a redefinition of the term "Nation", as it is applied to "Indian Nations." Discussion of the name to be used for the Organization being formed at this meeting to fight to uphold treaty rights and bylaws. Some of the names proposed were: Washington State Indian Treaty Rights Organization, Northwest Indian Treaty Rights Organization, Indian Fishing Rights Organization etc. John Solomon from Lummi speaks about the role of the Tribal Councils in the newly formed Treaty Rights organization. Chairman speaks about the intended purpose of the Affiliated Tribes of Northwest Indians as a functioning group. John Solomon speaks about the effectiveness of the Affiliated Tribes of Northwest Indians, and the need for bylaws within the organization.
    Tape 50, Side Two: [Recording is poor.] More discussion on the proposed names for the new organization. Discussion on the need for Native groups to be able to unite and try to solve issues in common. The Chairman addresses the issue of the benefit of making the new organization a corporation. The Chairman calls for resolutions from every tribe that wishes to be a part of the new Treaty Rights organization. Discussion of funds for future actions and formations of new organizations. Discussion of aboriginal hunting and fishing rights versus the hunting and fishing rights allowed in the Treaties, and the current pressures from the State level bureaucrats upon Indian tribes to conform to State regulations on hunting and fishing. Discussion on the right to erect smokehouses on the river banks.
  - Affiliated Tribes of Northwest Indians Executive Council Meeting, Spokane, Washington: Resolutions (Part I), 1973 April 12 (Box 1, Tape 51)
    Tape 51, Side One: Preamble and bylaws of the organization. Certain representatives give resolutions, and motions are made. Resolution for the cooperation and coordination of the NTCA and Northwest Affiliated Tribes Organization. Resolution on the appointment of new board members.
    Tape 51, Side Two: Resolutions and motions continue. Resolution and discussion on the display for the upcoming Expo. Education Committee presents their resolutions.
  - Affiliated Tribes of Northwest Indians Executive Council Meeting, Spokane, Washington: Resolutions (Part II), 1973 April 12 (Box 1, Tape 52)
    Tape 52, Side One: Resolution proposed by Cook and Trimble is discussed. Resolution to combat the BIA, right past wrongs by the Federal Government, and repeal Public Laws that have passed that violate the treaty rights of the tribe. John Solomon discusses the need for Indian voices to be acted on more than just heard. Some discussion over the distribution of funds to the NTCA and the NCAI. Some concluding statements focusing on the need for better communication.
    Tape 52, Side Two: Blank
  - Affiliated Tribes of Northwest Indians Executive Council Meeting, Spokane, Washington: Resolutions (Part III), 1973 April 13 (Box 1, Tape 53)
    Tape 53, Side One: A roll is called for the delegates present at the meeting. Speaker reads the first of the resolutions. Jim McKay of Lummi seconds the resolution and it is passed. Speaker reads the second resolution, which had to do with the reevaluation of the Environmental Protection Policy Act. The Speaker is asked to clarify the Environmental Protection Act, and how it is effecting the Native communities around the country. Speaker presents a resolution for the repeal/revision of Public Law 9335, which negatively effects the Spokane Tribe. Resolution to pressure the Federal government to right past wrongs committed against the Indian tribes.
    Tape 53, Side Two: [Tape quality is poor.] Resolution concerning third party approval on grants for tribes. Other resolutions are proposed and adopted. Resolution concerning aid to Urban Indian Centers. Resolution concerning the delegation of funds to repair and restore Chemawa Indian school. Resolutions to promote self-determination.
  - Nooksack Women: Louisa George, Helen Paul, and Ella Reid (Part I), 1973 May 9 (Box 1, Tape 54)
    Tape 54: This is a duplicate copy of Tape 37 in this same collection, only this copy is much clearer and will be used to edit the transcript that was rendered from Tape 37). Transcript available.
  - Nooksack Women: Louisa George, Helen Paul, and Ella Reid (Part II), 1973 May 9 (Box 1, Tape 55)
    Tape 55, Side One: Interview begins in progress. Louisa speaks about a religious leader. Helen Paul speaks about going to Chemawa and Mount Baker High School. Helen speaks about escaping the prejudiced nature of the boarding schools. Ella Reid speaks about her children's experience with the local school system. Louisa testifies to Helen having more problems being Pentecost than being Indian. Jeff Wilner asks about the Shaker Church attendance. Louisa and Helen discuss which families in Nooksack are affiliated with the Shaker Church. Helen speaks about attending a Shaker service. Helen and Louisa describe the doings at a Shaker Service. Ella, Louisa and Helen recall the songs sung in Indian at a Shaker service. Louisa tells the story of the formation of the Shaker church with the resurrection of John Slocum. Helen speaks about the dancing and singing that is part of the Shaker Church. Jeff Wilner asks about the Native American Church following in the area. Louisa speaks about her experience dancing in the Shaker Church. Louisa speaks about being a Pentecost after trying out the Shaker Church. Jeff Wilner asks about the railroad being built through Nooksack land without compensation. Helen speaks about a verbal agreement between the Nooksack people and the railroad company, which didn't come to pass. Helen mentions a lease that was made by the Nooksack people and that wasn't signed by the railroad. Helen and Louisa speak about riding the ferry to Victoria, and from Port Townsend, and receiving half-price fare. Helen speaks about the Coupeville races. Ella speaks about George Swanaset and his half-brother and Henry George (Sam George's uncle) racing at Carlisle. Ella speaks about the entrance process to race at Carlisle. Transcript available.
    Tape 55, Side Two: Blank
  - Master copies of interviews on cassette tapes, 1963-1973 (Box Box 2)
  - Reference and back-up copies of interviews on CDs in mp3 and WAV formats, 1963-1973 (Box Boxes 3 and 4)
- Transcripts, 1967-1973; Series II
  - Nina Baumgarner (Tape 7), 1973 May 4 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Joe Louie (Tape 11), 1973 May 24 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Nettie Shawaway (Tape 14), 1973 May 8 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Ramona Morris (Tape 22), 1973 Spring (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Al Charles (Tape 23), 1973 April 26 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Felix Solomon, Dora Solomon, Angeline Alexander and Aurelia Celestine (Part I: Tape 25), 1973 April 13 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Felix Solomon, Dora Solomon, Angeline Alexander and Aurelia Celestine (Part II: Tape 26), 1973 April 13 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Angeline Alexander (Part I: Tape 28), 1967 January 27 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Angeline Alexander (Part 2: Tape 29), 1967 January 27 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Louisa George, Sarah James, Ella Reid, Philoemina Solomon (Harry), Helen Paul, Rosemary Placid and Ernest Paul, (Part I: Tape 33), 1973 April 27 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Louisa George, Sarah James, Ella Reid, Philoemina Solomon (Harry), Helen Paul, Rosemary Placid and Ernest Paul, (Part II: Tape 33), 1973 April 27 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Joe Louie and Nooksack Women (Part I: Tape 35), 1973 May 1 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Joe Louie and Nooksack Women (Part I: Tape 35), 1973 May 1 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Louisa George, Ella Reid, and Helen Paul (Tape 37), 1973 May 9 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Morrie Alexander (Tape 40), 1973 April 12 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Christine Bosler, James McKay, James McKay Jr., and Rosemary Placid (Part I: Tape 42), 1973 June 1 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Christine Bosler, James McKay, James McKay Jr., and Rosemary Placid (Part II: Tape 43), 1973 June 1 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Louisa George, Helen Paul, and Ella Reid (Tape 55), 1973 May 9 (Box 5, Folder 18)